<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Security on perl11 blog</title>
    <link>http://perl11.org/blog/tags/security.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Security on perl11 blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© 2016 Copyright Reini Urban</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://perl11.org/blog/tags/security.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Unicode Identifiers</title>
      <link>http://perl11.org/blog/unicode-identifiers.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://perl11.org/blog/unicode-identifiers.html</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;binary-names-with-5-16&#34;&gt;Binary names with 5.16&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With perl 5.16 added support for binary names, announcing it as
support for unicode names. Unicode names were already supported since
5.8.4 with a negative length stored in the hash key of the symbol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supporting binary names without any supporting measures opened huge
security holes, as names are mapped 1:1 to filenames when searching
for a package, and as we know the C API for files or names just
ignores a \0, leading to inconsistencies. And you could now easily
hide payloads in package names. Remember that p5p never announced this
problem and feature, they only announced it as improved and full
unicode support for names.  In the following years I had to fix most
of the problems with binary names support, but many critical modules
still have no idea, and are still vulnerable. Even the new perl5
maintainer has no idea as he showed in his YAPC talk about XS
programming. He happily used the old &lt;code&gt;gv_&lt;/code&gt; interfaces not supporting
\0, and there&amp;rsquo;s no upgrade path in perl5 for old modules to avoid those
security holes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, with unicode this would not have been a big problem, as our used
encoding UTF-8 does not support \0. It&amp;rsquo;s also illegal.
Only with cperl-5.26 we finally got back safe names, \0 is illegal again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;unicode-security&#34;&gt;Unicode Security&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here we want to talk about the unicode problems when a language
decides to embrace unicode names. perl5 prides itself by being one of
the scripting languages with the best unicode support.  Well, the
libraries and strings, yes. But the language itself is still horribly
unicode unsafe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unicode consortium published many security addendums, as TRnn.
Most of them are targetted to html forms, domains names used in
browsers or DNS servers, and email names. The problem with unicode is,
that different names are not identifiable as such, and thus you can
easily fool someone to click on a wrong url. Identifiers need to be
identifiable and restricted.  perl5 and perl6 pride themselves of
anything goes, it does not enforce opinions on their users. Well, it&amp;rsquo;s
still insecure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simpliest unicode problems are tricks with illegal UTF-8
encodings.  This is also relevant to strings and therefore mostly
fixed in perl5 and cperl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are many more security problems in most programming
languages with unicode support. Only cperl, python3 and perl6 fixed
some of them, by doing normalization of its identifiers.
I didn&amp;rsquo;t see any effort in all the others, besides java.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most basic overview is at &lt;a href=&#34;http://websec.github.io/unicode-security-guide/&#34;&gt;http://websec.github.io/unicode-security-guide/&lt;/a&gt;.
Go read it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Because Unicode contains such a large number of characters and
 incorporates the varied writing systems of the world, incorrect usage
 can expose programs or systems to possible security attacks. This is
 especially important as more and more products are
 internationalized. This document describes some of the security
 considerations that programmers, system analysts, standards
 developers, and users should take into account, and provides specific
 recommendations to reduce the risk of problems.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important documents are&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unicode.org/reports/tr31/#Table_Candidate_Characters_for_Exclusion_from_Identifiers&#34;&gt;TR31 Candidate Characters for Exclusion from Identifiers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unicode.org/reports/tr36/&#34;&gt;TR36 Unicode Security Considerations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unicode.org/reports/tr39/&#34;&gt;TR39 Unicode Security Mechanisms&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, those problems need to be fixed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;mixed-scripts&#34;&gt;Mixed scripts&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A written language is defined by its scripts (i.e. &amp;ldquo;alphabets&amp;rdquo;). Some
languages allow multiple scripts, such as modern Japanese uses both
logographic (kanji, originated from Chinese hanzi&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) and syllabic
(kana) characters simultaneously, with two distinct types of kana
(hiragana and katakana).  So if you want to support japanese you need
allow all these three scripts to be used in a program, without any
declaration. Similar for Korean, which sometimes also use some old
Han/Chinese characters, and Chinese which uses the biggest set of
characters Han, plus one additional educational script, called
Bopomofo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is very apparent with Cyrillic and Greek. Both are
different languages, but use almost the same characters, which are not
identifiable in any font. If the character is a Greek or Cyrillic
symbol, or if it&amp;rsquo;s one of the mathematical symbols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So strict mixed-script profiles for identifiers forbid the default
usage of Greek and Cyrillic characters in the same program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In cperl, which is currently the only unicode safe language, this
is forbidden:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;use utf8;
my $Γ = 1;
if ($Г) { warn; }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;use utf8&lt;/code&gt; declares that identifiers can be unicode, utf-8 encoded.
&lt;code&gt;my $Γ = 1&lt;/code&gt; sets a scalar lexical variable to 1, with the name &lt;code&gt;Γ&lt;/code&gt;.
What you don&amp;rsquo;t see, only the parser, or if you inspect the program
binary, e.g. with od, is that the first Γ character is the greek
gamma, and the second variable uses the cyrillic gamma.
Only with a restricted identifier profile you will see the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;cperl does this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ cperl5.26.0 -e&#39;use utf8;my $Γ = 1;if ($Г) { warn }&#39;
Invalid script Cyrillic in identifier Г) { warn }
for U+0413. Have Greek at -e line 1.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I.e. it allows the first greek character in a name to be used without
declaration of a foreign script, but then fails when a cyrillic
character in a name appears. With such characters in strings or
buffers the user has to care, but with identifiers the parser has to
care, as the identifier is not identifiable anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a user really wants to use names in multiple languages in a
program, he needs to declare them beforehand, so the casual reader is
aware of the mixed scripts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;use utf8 (&amp;quot;Greek&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Cyrillic&amp;quot;);
my $Γ = 1;
if ($Г) { warn }&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;is now the valid variant. But note that mixing Cyrillic and Greek is
still frowned upon, and needs to be warned, even when being declared
as such.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarily, some scripts can be used undeclared, and some need to be
declared.  These recommendations are all specified in the TR39
Restriction levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;visual-spoofing&#34;&gt;Visual spoofing&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unicode is pretty good in defining what characters are allowed as
first character in an identifier, and what characters may
follow. These classes are declared in the &lt;code&gt;ID_Start&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code&gt;ID_Continue&lt;/code&gt;, see
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unicode.org/reports/tr31/#Table_Lexical_Classes_for_Identifiers&#34;&gt;TR 31 Lexical_Classes_for_Identifiers&lt;/a&gt;
for the precise rules properly used in most languages with unicode
support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know only of one bug in these tables, the U+3164 HANGUL FILLER is
wrongly specified as ID_Cont. Thus in perl5 this is valid:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ perl -e&#39;use utf8; $aㅤb == 2;&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but cperl detects the problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ cperl -e&#39;use utf8; $aㅤb == 2;&#39;
Unrecognized character \x{3164}; marked by &amp;lt;-- HERE after e utf8; $a&amp;lt;-- HERE
near column 13 at -e line 1.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Same problem for the U+ffa0 HALFWIDTH HANGUL FILLER. See also
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jagracey/Awesome-Unicode#user-content-variable-identifiers-can-effectively-include-whitespace&#34;&gt;https://github.com/jagracey/Awesome-Unicode#user-content-variable-identifiers-can-effectively-include-whitespace&lt;/a&gt;
According to according to
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unicode.org/L2/L2006/06310-hangul-decompose9.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.unicode.org/L2/L2006/06310-hangul-decompose9.pdf&lt;/a&gt; those two
fillers ᅟ..ᅠ HANGUL CHOSEONG FILLER..HANGUL JUNGSEONG FILLER are the
proper replacements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But besides those rare bugs, spoofs and confusables are much more common.
I only know of very few languages which actually detect those problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spoofs are certain trick character combinations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popular spoof attacks were the Paypal.com IDN spoof of 2005. Setup to
demonstrate the power of these attack vectors, Eric Johanson and The
Schmoo Group successfully used a www.paypal.com lookalike domain name
to fool visitors into providing personal information. The advisory
references original research from 2002 by Evgeniy Gabrilovich and Alex
Gontmakher at the Israel Institute of Technology. Their original paper
described an attack using Microsoft.com as an example. - &lt;a href=&#34;http://websec.github.io/unicode-security-guide/visual-spoofing/&#34;&gt;visual-spoofing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A typical bidi-spoof would involve a unicode aware text-editor or
viewer, and identifiers which switch to right-to-left (arabic),
overwrite the previous characters, and maybe even switch back to
left-to-right. Visually the names look the same, but internally the
spoofed name is much longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such spoofs are usually prevented with forbidding mixed scripts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;normalization&#34;&gt;Normalization&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other simple spoofs can be be prevented with normalization. This is
what Python3 started to do, also cperl and java.  With normalization
of unicode character sequences all possible and valid character
combinations are compressed to one single normal form. There are two
defined normal forms, NFKC and NFC, interestingly python decided to
pick the wrong one, normalizing to ligatures. cperl normalizes to the
canonical normal form NFC. perl6 decided to normalize to their own
format, called NFD, which allows invalid, private reserved characters
in upper planes, which will be forbidden in upcoming perl5 and cperl
releases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E.g. &lt;code&gt;café&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;c, a, f, e, U+0301&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;) is normalized to &lt;code&gt;café&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;c, a, f, U+00E9&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;code&gt;café́&lt;/code&gt;, using two combining marks (&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;c, a, f, e, U+0301, U+0301&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;) is currently allowed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;same-script-confusables&#34;&gt;Same Script Confusables&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a whole table of confusables which are still confusable after
restricting mixed scripts and after normalization.
These confusables are typically optionally warned upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;moderately-restrictive-level&#34;&gt;Moderately Restrictive Level&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;cperl as first dynamic scripting language follows the &lt;strong&gt;General
Security Profile&lt;/strong&gt; for identifiers in programming languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moderately Restrictive&lt;/strong&gt;: Allow &lt;code&gt;Latin&lt;/code&gt; with other Recommended or
Aspirational scripts except &lt;code&gt;Cyrillic&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Greek&lt;/code&gt;. Otherwise, the same as
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unicode.org/reports/tr39/#Identifier_Characters&#34;&gt;Highly Restrictive&lt;/a&gt;,
i.e. allow &lt;code&gt;:Japanese&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;:Korean&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;:Hanb&lt;/code&gt; aliases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Some characters are not in modern customary use, and thus implementations
may want to exclude them from identifiers.  These include characters in
historic and obsolete scripts, scripts used mostly liturgically, and
regional scripts used only in very small communities or with very limited
current usage.  The set of characters in Table 4, Candidate Characters for
Exclusion from Identifiers provides candidates of these.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;cperl honors the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unicode.org/reports/tr31/#Table_Candidate_Characters_for_Exclusion_from_Identifiers&#34;&gt;TR31 Candidate Characters for Exclusion from Identifiers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I.e. You may still declare those scripts as valid, but they are not
automatically allowed, similar to the need to declare mixed scripts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;use utf8;
my $ᭅ = 1; # \x{1b45} BALINESE LETTER KAF SASAK

=&amp;gt; Invalid script Balinese in identifier ᭅ for U+1B45
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but when declared as such:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;use utf8 &#39;Balinese&#39;;
my $ᭅ = 1; # \x{1b45} BALINESE LETTER KAF SASAK
print &amp;quot;ok&amp;quot;;

=&amp;gt; ok
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scripts listed at &amp;ldquo;Table 6, Aspirational Use Scripts&amp;rdquo;:
&lt;code&gt;Canadian_Aboriginal&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Miao&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Mongolian&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Tifinagh&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Yi&lt;/code&gt;
are included, i.e. need not to be declared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this restriction we are close to the implementation of the
Moderately Restrictive level for identifiers by default. See
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unicode.org/reports/tr39/#General_Security_Profile&#34;&gt;http://www.unicode.org/reports/tr39/#General_Security_Profile&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unicode.org/reports/tr36/#Security_Levels_and_Alerts&#34;&gt;http://www.unicode.org/reports/tr36/#Security_Levels_and_Alerts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With special declarations of the used scripts you can weaken the
restriction level to &lt;strong&gt;Minimally Restrictive&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Missing for the &lt;strong&gt;Moderately Restrictive&lt;/strong&gt; level are warnings on
single-, mixed and whole-script confusables, and warnings on certain
incompatible mixed-script pairs such as &lt;strong&gt;Greek + Cyrillic&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All utf8 encoded names are checked for wellformed-ness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;comments-at-r-cperl-https-www-reddit-com-r-cperl-comments-5y063u-unicode-identifiers&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/cperl/comments/5y063u/unicode_identifiers/&#34;&gt;Comments at /r/cperl/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;In Unicode, they&amp;rsquo;re generally unified into a single set, via a process called &amp;ldquo;Han unification&amp;rdquo;. So, unlike Greek &amp;ldquo;Α&amp;rdquo; vs Cyrillic &amp;ldquo;А&amp;rdquo;, the &amp;ldquo;same&amp;rdquo; character that may even look slightly differently in Chinese vs Japanese (e.g. &amp;ldquo;海&amp;rdquo;), would have a single codepoint in Unicode.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The dangerous SipHash myth</title>
      <link>http://perl11.org/blog/seed.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2016 12:35:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://perl11.org/blog/seed.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SipHash claims that its &amp;ldquo;cryptographically strong pseudo random
function&amp;rdquo; properties protects against hash table DoS flood attacks.
This is wrong, because for a successful attack against a SipHash hash
table with chained linked lists or linear probing it is enough to get
the secret random seed, and then brute force create collisions, which
is doable in &amp;lt;1s for 16k keys, 2m for 16k keys, and from 32k to 268M
keys in 4 minutes. For any hash function, SipHash, AES or even SHA256.
Which is far from being secure. Declaring a hash function for a hash
table secure is wrong and pure security theatre, which unfortunately
a lot of people started to believe in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally you can prepare collisions offline, but as you see you can
even create them online as soon as you know the seed.  Inserting 64k
keys needs 32 seconds vs 0.01 seconds on e.g. PHP, from constant to
quadratic, with an amplification factor of 200.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://events.ccc.de/congress/2011/Fahrplan/events/4680.en.html&#34;&gt;https://events.ccc.de/congress/2011/Fahrplan/events/4680.en.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the only protection is the secrecy of the random seed, which has
nothing to do with any properties of SipHash per se. A hash
function can never protect a hash table from hash flood attacks on
hash tables with simple lists on collisions. SipHash properties are
that is not reversible, the seed is mixed in the box and not only
at the beginning, so it&amp;rsquo;s is hard to get the seed from the hash
function itself. But there&amp;rsquo;s no need for it, as it is trivial to
get the seed via other means. The collisions are prone to timing
attacks independent on the hash function, usually the hash
iterator exposes the inner ordering and in most cases the random
seed is exposable via traditional memory exposure. If the seed is
hash table specific or global, i.e. process or thread specific.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E.g. in debian perl you get the seed at process startup via&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ PERL_HASH_SEED_DEBUG=1 /usr/bin/perl -e0
=&amp;gt; HASH_FUNCTION = ONE_AT_A_TIME_HARD HASH_SEED = 0xd12d459fc36db4cf PERTURB_KEYS = 1 (RANDOM)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to stderr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On centos7:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ PERL_HASH_SEED_DEBUG=1 /usr/bin/perl -e0
=&amp;gt; HASH_SEED = 10452142639498245987
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Older centos 5 and 6 has an unpatched perl hash table function which
is vulnerable to much simplier DoS attacks, which is e.g. used on the
redhat openshift public cloud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a running perl process the seed is at a known fixed offset.  Which
is easily readable via some kind of poke function via the unpack &amp;ldquo;P&amp;rdquo;
builtin op. See Devel::PeekPoke.  Similar for all other dynamic
languages exposing the value of any pointer. Which is esp. problematic
for languages who trusted the false claims of the SipHash authors,
that using this secure hash function it makes it safe against such DoS
attacks. Which are most prominently ruby, python, rust, haskell and
others.  Perl5 at least changed the order of the iterator, cperl
counts the collisions and adds a sleep on attacks, PHP limits the size
of external keys to be passed to the hash table so only JSON or other
formats are easily DoS-able. But more serious applications such as the
linux kernel, glibc, cache or DNS servers use better hash table
collisions schemes than unsafe chaining or linear probing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vulnerable are all implementors of hash tables who believed the false
claims of the SipHash authors: ruby, python, rust, haskell, OpenBSD
and some more.  But also others who don&amp;rsquo;t use a proper hash table
collision resolution scheme or don&amp;rsquo;t protect their seed or easily
expose the seed, such as perl5 and many more.  rust currently
e.g. believes that SipHash makes it secure even if a trivial attack
was just found against it, and changing the seed at table resize will
help. It only helps a bit.  The seed is still exposable.  With an
amplification factor of 200 with a table size large enough there&amp;rsquo;s
enough attack surface to render a service useless.
Reseeding on resize will lead to an amplification factor of 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Links:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/google/highwayhash/issues/28&#34;&gt;google/highwayshash False security claims&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rurban/smhasher/#security&#34;&gt;SMHasher on Security&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rurban/perl-hash-stats&#34;&gt;perl hash stats&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>